PEDESTRIANS AND BICYCLES ONLY
（行人和自行车专用）
2017, fall.
2017年秋
NURSE STATION PATIENT ROOMS
（护士站 病房）
My uncle was struck by a truck when he was 17.
我舅舅在17岁那年被一辆卡车撞倒
After 17 years of being in a coma…
在陷入昏迷17年之后
he awoke.
突然醒了过来
Irellars Granbahamal tona galtoeba rilex.
伊雷拉斯格兰巴哈马尔 托纳加尔托巴里雷克斯
He had gone insane.
他变得不正常了
Yes, well…
是的 那个…
Japanese?
日语？
Sorry about that.
真是抱歉
I just came back from spending 17 years in Granbahamal.
我在格兰巴哈马尔过了17年 刚刚回来
Let's check your temperature.
该量体温了
Zalbe madira kolstonam kolstonam.
扎勒贝马蒂哈科尔斯通南科尔斯通南
Isn't that right?
可不是吗？
Del storba tona rabelt gal.
戴尔斯托巴托纳拉贝尔特加尔
All right, see you during the next round.
好的 下次查房时见
You must be Takafumi, my sister's kid.
你一定就是我姐姐的孩子敬文
You've grown up.
已经长大成人了
Where is everyone?
大家都在哪？
After you fell into a coma,
在你陷入昏迷后
the family fought bitterly over what to do with you until it fell apart.
家里人不知道该拿你怎么办 吵得很厉害 最后都分开了
Honestly speaking, my mom would rather not see you.
说实话 我妈妈不愿见到你
MY FAMILY FELL APART DUE TO FIGHTING OVER ME
（因为我的事 家人离散）
Icuras cuora.
伊库拉斯库奥拉
Well then,
那好
let me prove to you that I lived in another world.
让我证明给你看 我曾生活在另一个世界里
What? No, thanks.
什么？不用了 谢谢
War-grent seld.
沃哥伦特塞尔德
SPRING WATER
（矿泉水）
What?
怎么回事？
War-grent magna!
沃哥伦特马格纳！
War-grent rald!
沃哥伦特拉尔德！
-This is hard to watch… -War-grent neld!
-真不忍心看下去… -沃哥伦特内尔德！
War-grent gad!
沃哥伦特加德！
War-grent pad!
沃哥伦特帕德！
-You know… -War-grent larch!
-你要知道… -沃哥伦特拉奇！
…the economic decline has been hard on me, too.
我也受到了经济衰退的打击
I work part-time to support myself.
靠做兼职养活自己
I brought papers for you to apply for self-reliance support and whatnot.
我带了些文件 你可以申请自力更生支持项目什么的
Wind, lift!
风 起！
No way!
这不可能！
Wind, return.
风 散
Japanese works in this world.
在这个世界得说日语才能起作用
It's true.
这是真的
Anyway, were you about to hit me with harsh reality just now?
对了 你刚才是不是正打算 用严酷的现实打击我？
-Nope. -You sure?
-没有 -你确定？
What did you do just now?
刚刚你那一手是怎么回事？
Magic.
魔法
Fire.
火
That's amazing! How do you do that?
太神奇了！你是怎么做到的？
Never mind it.
你别管了
Who's winning the Console War? Is it SEGA?
谁赢得了游戏机之战？是世嘉吗？
What?
什么？
SEGA? Nowadays?
世嘉？如今吗？
In Japan, Sony and Nintendo dominate the industry.
在日本 索尼和任天堂统治了游戏业
What? What about SEGA?
什么？那世嘉呢？
-Is that something you need to know-- -What about SEGA?
-你真的想知道… -那世嘉呢？
Well… it gave up making consoles a good while ago.
嗯…早就放弃制造游戏机了
Icuras cuora.
伊库拉斯库奥拉
What does "icuras cuora" do?
“伊库拉斯库奥拉”有什么作用？
This spell erases memories.
这句咒语能抹除记忆
I use it when things get unbearable.
当事情变得让人无法忍受时 我就会使用它
Is SEGA's decline such a big shock to him?
世嘉的败落对他打击那么大吗？
The other world was fraught with difficulties.
异世界的生活困难重重
Want to take a look?
你想看看吗？
Oh, sure.
当然了
Make me forget everything I read just now.
让我忘记自己刚读到的一切吧
I told you.
早跟你说了
Spirits of memory, deliver unto oblivion.
记忆之灵 施以忘却
SEGA's decline truly was heart-wrenching to him.
世嘉的败落真的让他很痛心
One week later…
一周之后…
I decided to make a living by making money off of my uncle's powers.
我决定靠舅舅的超能力赚钱生活
ANOTHER WORLD - LIGHTSABER
（异世界-光剑）
I uploaded videos on YouTube
我在油管上传了视频
and earned about 60,000 yen from ads.
靠广告赚了六万日元
UNCLE: YOU'RE FINE THE WAY YOU ARE
（舅舅：你这样就挺好）
GET HOME
（回家）
SOLD CHEAPER THAN A SCOURING PAD
（卖得比洗碗布还便宜）
I shouldn't say this, since I'm crashing, but isn't this unit too big for just you?
话不该这么说 我是白吃白住 但这间公寓对你来说不太大了吗？
Yeah, I used to share this room with someone else,
是的 我以前是跟别人合住的
but I had troubles with them.
但跟相处得不好
A roommate? Was it a girlfriend?
室友？是女朋友吗？
Well, no…
那个 不是…
Wow…
哇…
No, it's called a room share! Haven't you heard of it?
不是的 这叫拼房 你没听说过吗？
No.
没有
HISTORY OF ROOM SHARE
（拼房记录）
There was no such thing 17 years ago?
17年前没这种事吗？
Wow, you looked that up in seconds.
哇 这么快就查到了
Electronic dictionaries sure have evolved.
电子词典演变得好快
Yep… Wait, what?
是的…等等 什么？
Little Takafumi…
小敬文…
is old enough to recruit friends and live with them.
已经长大 可以交朋友同居了
What were your friends like in the other world?
你在异世界的朋友是什么样的？
I basically played solo for 17 years.
我基本上就是自己打了17年的游戏
Is that right…
是吗？
Everyone over there is good-looking.
那边的人都很好看
They're all handsome men and beautiful women.
不是俊男就是美女
That's great.
那很好啊
I must have looked ugly…
我看上去一定很丑…
I was hunted down as an orc variant.
被当成半兽人的亚种而遭到追捕
Uncle, hold on.
舅舅 等等
-Then-- -It's too heavy!
-然后… -这个话题太沉重了！
I don't want to hear this while washing the dishes.
我不想在洗碗时听到这个
That's how it usually went, but some were particularly aggressive.
一般都是这样 但有些人尤其可恶
I told you to wait!
我说了让你等等！
They followed me around every day and pestered and harassed me.
他们每天到处跟着我 纠缠骚扰
No matter what I did, they made fun of me and wouldn't let me be who I am.
无论我做什么 他们都加以取笑 不让我做真正的自己
How horrible…
多么可怕…
So that's the reality of a parallel world fantasy life.
所以这才是平行世界 奇幻生活的真实状况啊
I saved her life when I met her. She didn't even thank me.
我遇到她时救了她一命 她都没有谢过我
She sounds like the worst.
听上去她人很差劲
Right?
是吧？
She said, "No one asked for your help. Don't touch me!
她当时说：“没人向你求助 别碰我！
Don't misinterpret it. I didn't save you for your sake.
你不要误会 我救你并不是为了你好
I must be the only one who can stand being with an orc face like you!"
你长得这么像半兽人 一定只有我才受得了跟你在一起！”
She berated me to no end.
她无休无止地数落我
I got rid of her in some city and took off.
我在一个城镇甩掉她 自己走了
Don't touch me!
别碰我！
Don't misinterpret me!
你不要误会！
I must be the only one who can stand being with an orc face like you.
你长得这么像半兽人 一定只有我才受得了跟你在一起
The concept of tsundere became popular around 2004.
“傲娇”这个概念大约是2004年流行开来的
Four years after my uncle left for the other world.
也就是舅舅前往异世界四年之后
What happened to her afterwards?
她后来怎么样了？
What? Who knows?
什么？这谁知道？
Anyway, my life didn't go well in the other world, either.
总之 我在异世界的日子也不好过
But now I've come back,
但现在我回来了
there's the Internet, optical fiber, and even "wii-fii"!
能享受互联网、光纤 甚至还有“五仙网络”！
This is great!
太爽了！
With videos, even I can connect with people from around the world.
借助视频 连我都能跟全世界的人交流
What?
什么？
EVEN A 5TH GRADER LIKE ME CAN TELL HOW FAKE THIS IS.
（连五年级学生都能看出来有多假）
SUCH AMATEUR EDITING. IS IT A BAD JOKE?
（剪辑太业余 是冷笑话吗？）
My uncle, who returned from the other world…
我从异世界归来的舅舅…
LOLOL - MAD FACE UNCLE
（哇哈哈-气红脸舅舅）
…stepped into a brand-new world, the Internet.
…进入了一个全新的世界 互联网
What? How can they see my face?
什么？他们怎么能看到我的脸？
-Maybe through this tiny lens? -It's what people say on the Internet.
-也许是通过这个小摄像头？ -这是大家在网上的评论啊
A "sock puppet"? I'm not a hoax!
“马甲”？我不是骗子！
Those are commonly used phrases. Nothing more.
这都是常用语而已
Hey, why is "LOL" everywhere?
嘿 怎么到处都是“哈哈”？
He doesn't know how to deal with haters yet.
他还不知道怎么应付喷子们
MEMORY INTO OBLIVION - THANKS
（忘却记忆-谢谢）
USED - GOOD
（二手-状态良好）
I want this cell phone.
我想要这款手机
It doesn't open up but slides around.
不是翻盖 而是侧向滑动的
Uncle, that one's a 2G.
舅舅 那是第二代通信技术手机
Can I buy it through this online auction?
我能通过网络拍卖买下来吗？
You can't make calls on it since it uses an outdated radio wave.
它使用的电波已经过时 无法用来打电话
That's fine. I don't care about calls.
没关系 我不在乎能否打电话
What about your junior high and high school friends?
你在初中和高中的那些朋友们呢？
Takafumi,
敬文
a man who chooses SEGA console cannot live an ordinary life.
选择世嘉游戏机的人无法过平凡的生活
PERSONAL OPINION
（个人见解）
Why do game consoles dictate so much of his life?
为什么游戏机 对他的生活有那么大的影响？
That one looks like the cheapest option.
那个好像是最便宜的
You already researched it.
你已经做过研究了
Those smartphones may be tiny, but they sure are powerful.
这些智能手机是很小 但功能强大
You'll soon get the hang of it.
你很快就能掌握要领的
"Touch," "swipe," "pinch out"…
“轻触”、“滑动”、“放大”…
For now, I want a phone with lots of buttons.
目前 我还是想要一部有很多按键的手机
Yeah?
是吗？
But the cool ones that open up, slide, or spin around are all gone.
但那些能够打开 滑动或旋转的爆款都没有了
Technological innovation. Everyone uses touch panel phones now.
多亏了技术革新 现在大家都在使用触摸屏手机
That's 17 years of innovation.
历时17年的革新
Actually, I made a technological advancement in the other world.
其实我在异世界也取得了一项技术成果
What did you invent?
你发明了什么？
I created a vase that poured out water in a drought-stricken village.
我在一个遭遇旱灾的村子 制作出了能倒出水来的大瓶子
Awesome! How did you do that?
真厉害！你是怎么做到的？
I used two spells to…
我用了两句咒语来…
It'll be easier to show you my memory.
让你看看我的记忆更省事
Icuras elran.
伊库拉斯埃尔兰
This image!
这幅景象！
It's your memory from the other world!
是你在异世界的记忆！
These magic-storing cards are called talismans.
这些魔法存储卡被称为符咒
I'll forgo the details, but it worked by reversing the water electrolysis process.
细节我就不说了 原理就是逆转水电解的过程
Modern science is undefeated!
现代科技所向匹敌！
Uncle, you dominated the other world.
舅舅 你主宰了异世界
The people must have sung your praises and revered you.
大家一定对你赞誉有加 奉若神明
Not really.
并非如此
They tried to hang me.
他们想绞死我
The vase, smashed to smithereens.
那个瓶子被砸得粉碎
It wasn't acceptable in their religion.
这在他们的信仰里是无法接受的
Hold it!
住手！
Someone came to rescue you.
有人来救你了
Yeah, that's the girl bent on harassing me.
她就是那个热衷于骚扰我的女孩
This girl?
是这个女孩？
Yes, he has an evil countenance. He is more like an orc than a man.
没错 他相貌邪恶 与其说像人类 不如说更像半兽人
I don't blame you for distrusting him, however--
你们不相信他 我不怪你们 但是…
War-grent grakka.
沃哥伦特格拉卡
That was rough…
刚才真悬…
That's how it went.
就是这么回事
Sorry.
真对不起
It's hard to see from the first-person view.
第一人称视角看着是很别扭
That bothers you?
你是因为这个觉得抱歉？
Swipe it like this to turn the camera.
像这样滑动 转一下摄像头
-Here we go. -How is that possible?
-好了 -这怎么可能？
Pinch in to make it smaller.
手指捏合缩小画面
They almost hunted you down.
他们差点抓到你
Can we see what happened to that girl?
我们能看看那个女孩怎么了吗？
Sure. Let's pinch out to enlarge.
当然可以 用手指放大一下
There she is.
她在那
That coward…
那个懦夫…
He ran away.
居然逃跑了
Goodness…
天哪…
What a kind girl! She's also super beautiful!
多好的女孩！而且超级漂亮！
That's right, I'm a coward.
没错 我是个懦夫
END OF AUCTION NOTIFICATION
（拍卖结束提醒）
Yes, the auction.
对了 拍卖
TIME LEFT
（剩余时间）
It's about to end!
就快结束了！
PLACE A BID
（出价竞拍）
I'm placing a bid!
我要出价！
What's the shipping cost?
运费是多少？
What?
什么？
AUCTION ENDED - CONGRATULATIONS! YOU WON!
（拍卖结束-恭喜！您竞拍成功！）
CHECK YOUR TRANSACTION
（查看您的交易）
BID WON - 1,600 YEN, SHIPMENT FEE - 2,000 YEN
（中标-1600日元 运费-2000日元）
The shipping is 2,000 yen.
运费是2000日元
It's shipped from a remote island I've never heard of.
发货地是一座偏远的岛屿 名字我从来没听说过
We don't have to pay for shipping if we pick it up in person.
要是我们自己去取 就不用支付运费
What?
什么？
Uncle!
舅舅！
I'll be back soon.
我很快就回来
30 MINUTES LATER
（30分钟后）
I'm back.
我回来了
Uncle…
舅舅…
How do you like this headphone?
你喜欢这幅耳机吗？
-Where is it auctioned from? -Kumamoto.
-拍卖地是哪？ -熊本
Five minutes tops.
最多用五分钟
How about this couch?
这个沙发呢？
Too heavy to haul around.
拖着太沉了
I'll give you a shoulder massage afterward.
事后我给你按摩肩膀
Well, okay then.
那好吧
My uncle learned how to buy online with free shipping.
我舅舅学会了 如何在线购买免费送货的物品
Thank you.
多谢
I could have gone to get it.
我可以自己去取的
This rice was on a special discount on Amazon.
这种米正在亚马逊上搞促销
Can you grab me a knife?
能帮我拿把小刀吗？
-Here you go. -Thanks.
-给 -谢谢
What's this? Where'd you get it?
这是什么？你哪来的？
Dimensional storage.
维度储物间
Also, this. It's for slaying dragons, so handle with caution.
还有啊 那是屠龙用的 所以要小心点
You had that at the hospital.
你在医院里就拿着这个
Do you have anything else from the other world?
你还有其他来自异世界的东西吗？
Certainly.
当然
I have this magic sword.
有这把魔法剑
My deposit…
我的租房押金…
I have precious metals, too.
我还有一些贵重金属
This crystallization of mermaid's tears was crafted with magic.
这种美人鱼眼泪的结晶是用魔法制成的
This ring is sculpted from rainbow coral.
这枚戒指是用彩虹珊瑚雕刻而成
This gem alone can pay to build a castle in the other world.
单是这颗宝石 就足够在异世界建造一座城堡
Let's sell it!
卖掉它！
Fifty yen.
只能卖50日元
I took it to a pawn shop.
我拿着它去过当铺
It was appraised for 50 yen.
估价只有50日元
It's a bit too rare.
有点太罕见了
Our views aren't growing.
观看次数没有增加
We need a breakthrough.
我们需要有突破
Uncle,
舅舅
did you have this ring because you meant to gift it to someone?
你留着这枚戒指 是不是想把它送给某个人？
Not really. Gems are more like memorabilia.
也不是 宝石更像是纪念品
They can only be obtained after beating challenging dungeons.
只有打败凶恶的地牢怪物才能得到
Is that so?
是吗？
You want to talk about relationships?
你想聊聊感情生活吗？
Not really. You don't seem interested in that kind of thing. So, no thanks.
不太想 你好像对那种事不感兴趣 所以不了 谢谢
Cut the nonsense. I've lived for over 30 years.
别胡说 我活了30多年
That comes with experience.
经验还是有一些的
I met my first love in grade school.
我是在小学里遇到初恋的
What were they like?
她们长什么样？
They were Sonic and Tails.
她们分别是索尼克和塔尔斯
What?
什么？
I stopped by the toy shop's display window every day and spent hours watching the TV.
我每天都会在玩具店的橱窗那停留 看好几个小时的电视
The title scene was so cute, I never got tired of it.
游戏片头那么可爱 我永远也看不够
Do you have any experience involving people?
你有跟人谈恋爱的经验吗？
Of course I do.
当然有了
Kaede Nanase was a good friend of mine.
七濑枫曾是我的好朋友
The enemy group's leader murdered her.
但为敌方头目所害
She was then revived as a living machine.
之后她作为一部活着的机器而复活
They relentlessly attack her to obtain the salvation weapon Seven Force.
他们无情地攻击她 想得到救赎武器“七力”
Stage three's boss is the fifth form of…
第三关的老怪是第五种形态的…
Does he have any experience outside of video games in his life?
他在生活中除了电子游戏 还有别的经历吗？
Did you meet any girls in the other world?
你在异世界遇到过女孩吗？
-I did. -What?
-遇到过 -什么？
Icuras elran.
伊库拉斯埃尔兰
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
And that's how I saved her from a monster.
这就是我从怪物手里救下她的经过
More like she offered her life in exchange for her brothers'.
更像是她为了救自己的弟弟 自愿以命抵命
Wasn't that smooth?
我很厉害吧？
Immediately afterward, I was struck from a blind spot by some goblins.
但我马上就被精灵从盲点袭击
They threw me off a cliff, and that was that.
然后被扔下悬崖 就这样了
What a disaster.
太惨了
The two brothers snuck behind him with terrifying looks on their faces.
看上去很可怕的那两兄弟 偷偷溜到了他背后
Let's check how that ambush occurred.
来看看他们是怎么伏击我的
I'm sure they were goblins.
肯定是精灵干的
-Yeah? -Yeah, absolutely!
-是吗？ -对 绝对是！
I was on the brink of death when she stumbled into me.
她遇到我的时候 我正处在死亡的边缘
I hate to say this, but she saved me.
我不想承认 但是她救了我
You…
你…
Why did you…
你为什么…
Don't you misunderstand.
你不要误会
You are indebted to me now.
你现在欠我人情
Spend the rest of your life bowing to me.
下半辈子都要听命于我
The rest of my life?
下半辈子？
What?
什么？
That's not what I meant.
我不是那个意思
I didn't mean "together forever" or anything.
我不是说“永远在一起”什么的
W-what? Stay away from me!
干吗？别靠近我！
I'd rather not owe you a huge favor.
我不愿欠你一份大人情
-Will this do? -What?
-这个可以吗？ -什么？
What?
什么？
It's a cosmite ring, said to be one of the only seven in existence.
这是柯斯米特戒指 据说是世上仅存的七枚之一
What are you doing?
你要干吗？
How does it fit?
戴着合适吗？
Wait, hold on!
等等 且慢！
It's too sudden…
这太突然了…
Do you not want it?
你不想要吗？
I do…
我想…
My uncle is about to do something outrageous!
我舅舅要做出惊世骇俗的事情了！
Was that okay to do?
这么做可以吗？
Looks like it means the same in the other world. Did you take responsibility?
看上去这在异世界也有定情之意 你有没有负起责任？
Of course I did.
当然有了
I was responsible enough to have it redeemed at the next town.
我非常负责任 在下一个镇子就拿它换了钱
Uncle!
舅舅！
You said you dodged her in some town. So it was this one.
你说你在某个城镇甩掉了她 看来是这里了
No. She kept following me around.
不 她一直跟着我
Maybe she got a taste for money.
也许她尝到了有钱的甜头
I deposited it at a bank. Where are you going next?
我把钱存入了银行 你接下来要去哪？
What? You'll stay here for now? What a coincidence. Me, too!
什么？你要暂时留在这里？ 真巧 我也是！
She's resilient.
她还真执着
As you can see,
你也看到了
these kinds of rare items can be useful on many occasions.
这种稀有物品在很多情况下都用得到
Let's stash that knife in here.
把刀也存放进去吧
Sure.
好的
UNCLE!?
（舅舅？）
My uncle's new video surpassed 2,000,000 views.
舅舅新视频的观看次数超过了两百万次
I'M ALIVE
（我还活着）
2017, fall.
2017年的秋天
My new life with my uncle
我跟舅舅在一起的新生活
had just begun.
开始了
Subtitle translation by: Minoru Nishikawa
字幕翻译：伍画